Before they came to this orphanage,
Bu yetimhaneye gelmeden önce birbirlerinden başka kimseleri yoktu.
When they were taken in at the border with Czechoslovakia,
Çekoslovakya sınırında bulunduklarında
they were trembling with cold and walking hand in hand.
soğuktan tir tir titriyorlar ve el ele yürüyorlardı.
I heard that the orphanages in the East were terrible.
Doğu Almanya'daki yetimhanelerin korkunç olduğunu duydum.
Please don't think that we are like Kinderheim 511.
Bizim 511. Yetimhane gibi olduğumuzu düşünme lütfen.
What?
Ne?
Inge. That's not the way to the bathroom.
Inge, tuvalet o tarafta değil.
Come on now.
Gel bakalım.
Mommy!
Anneciğim!
It's okay. Don't be scared.
Geçti. Korkma.
You can go to the bathroom by yourself, right?
Tek başına tuvalete gidebilirsin, değil mi?
Those children don't know what a parent's love is like.
Bu çocuklar anne baba sevgisi nedir bilmiyor.
People need love in order to grow.
İnsanın büyümesi için sevgi görmesi şart.
Just like you said, the orphanages in the East
Dediğin gibi, Doğu Almanya'daki yetimhaneler
were absolutely horrible.
tek kelimeyle korkunçtu.
This place used to be called Orphanage No. 47,
Buranın adı eskiden 47. Yetimhane'ydi
We didn't want to be controlled by the government.
Hükûmetin bizi kontrol etmesini istemedik.
At least, not like Kinderheim 511.
En azından 511. Yetimhane'yi kontrol ettiği gibi.
They were under the joint control of the Ministries of Health and the Interior.
511. Yetimhane
Do you know what that means?
Bu ne demek, biliyor musun?
No.
Hayır.
What went on there was controlled by the Ministry of the Interior.
Orada olan biteni içişleri bakanı kontrol ediyordu.
Because that place was
Çünkü orası
East Germany's experimental facility.
Doğu Almanya'nın deney tesisiydi.
Experimental facility?
Deney tesisi mi?
They were conducting a project
Çocukları kusursuz askerler hâline getirmek için
They altered the minds…
Çocukların zihinlerini…
and bodies of the children in their research.
…ve vücutlarını değiştirdiler.
They made the children form factions,
Çocuklara gruplar kurdurup
and they monitored how they hated and fought against each other.
birbirlerinden nasıl nefret ettiklerini, birbiriyle kavga ettiklerini izlediler.
It was an experiment
Deneyin amacı
to create cold-hearted people without compassion.
merhametsiz, taş kalpli insanlar yaratmaktı.
Can you imagine what kind of people
O çocuklar büyüdüğünde
those children would be when they grew up?
onların nasıl insanlar olduğunu hayal edebiliyor musun?
But now we don't have
Ama orada olanlara dair
any proof of what went down in there.
elimizde hiçbir delil yok.
It seems that everything about that was burned right before the Wall came down.
Orayla ilgili her şey duvar yıkılmadan hemen önce yakılmış.
Ministry of the Interior members who were involved fled as well.
Olayla ilgisi olan içişleri bakanlığı üyeleri de kaçmış.
However, I have heard one thing.
Ama bir şey duydum.
There was one person who successfully hid his personal history
Kendi geçmişini başarıyla saklayıp
and settled in this country.
bu ülkeye yerleşen bir kişi varmış.
That person was a supervisor
511. Yetimhane'nin
for Kinderheim 511's evil project.
bu şeytani projesinin denetmeniydi.
His true identity was
Gerçek kimliğine göre
a child psychologist for the Volkspolizei.
Volkspolizei bünyesinde bir çocuk psikoloğuydu.
But he would say he was a district officer for the Ministry of Health here.
Ama buradaki sağlık bakanlığında bölge memuru olduğunu söylüyor.
A district officer… for the Ministry of Health?
Sağlık bakanlığında bölge memuru mu?
Are you done, Inge?
Bitti mi Inge?
Yes.
Evet.
Sleep tight.
Tatlı rüyalar.
Come on.
Hadi.
Goodnight.
İyi geceler.
Everything is in the dark now because of that incident.
O olay yüzünden şu an her şey karanlığa gömülü.
The incident?
Olay mı?
What happened in Kinderheim 511?
511. Yetimhane'de ne oldu?
I guess I said too much now. It's reminded me of some terrible things.
Sanırım çok şey anlattım. Korkunç şeyleri aklıma getirdi.
Please tell me what happened at the place.
Orada ne olduğunu anlatın lütfen.
Where's the soccer ball?
Futbol topu nerede?
-Huh? -My…
-Ne? -Topum…
Where is my soccer ball?
Futbol topum nerede?
Here it is.
İşte, al bakalım.
But you can't play soccer until you're all healed.
Ama tamamen iyileşene dek futbol oynayamazsın.
The man said he would come and pick you up.
O adam gelip seni alacağını söyledi.
Until then, rest quietly here. Okay?
O gelene kadar sessizce dinlen, tamam mı?
I don't really know all the truth.
Gerçeği tam olarak bilmiyorum.
The East German government issued a strict gag order at the time.
Doğu Almanya hükûmeti o dönem katı bir konuşma yasağı getirdi.
It all started with the director's unnatural death.
Her şey müdürün doğal olmayan ölümüyle başladı.
Right after that, a dispute broke out
Ondan hemen sonra eğitmenler arasında
amongst the instructors over who would succeed the director.
müdürün yerine kimin geçeceğiyle ilgili bir tartışma başladı.
I heard that it was anarchy inside the orphanage.
Yetimhane içinde anarşi olduğunu duydum.
It was impossible to control the inner conflicts between the children as well.
Çocuklar arasındaki iç çatışmaları da kontrol etmek imkânsızdı.
I'm surprised that Johan managed to get out of there alive.
Johan'ın oradan sağ çıkabilmesine şaşırdım.
What happened to Kinderheim 511 after that?
Ondan sonra 511. Yetimhane'de ne oldu?
Everyone died.
Herkes öldü.
What?
Ne?
Including the instructors, all the members of the orphanage
Eğitmenler dâhil, yetimhanenin tüm üyeleri
killed each other.
birbirini öldürdü.
The world being a horrible place is a complete lie!
Dünyaya korkunç bir yer demek büyük yalan!
Tomorrow will be a good day.
Yarın güzel bir gün olacak.
Dieter.
Dieter.
Someone is here to pick you up.
Seni almaya gelen biri var.
Hey, Mr. Hartmann.
Hey, Bay Hartmann.
Aren't we going home?
Eve gitmiyor muyuz?
No, we will make a stop.
Hayır, bir yere uğrayacağız.
I don't want to go there.
Oraya gitmek istemiyorum.
No! I don't want to!
Hayır, istemiyorum işte!
Dieter.
Dieter.
Dieter, you're a good boy. Right?
Dieter, sen uslu bir çocuksun. Değil mi?
What?
Ne?
I told you not to let Dieter go with anyone until I return!
Ben dönene kadar Dieter'nın gitmesine izin vermeyin, dedim!
B… But…
Ama…
That man was his foster parent.
O adam koruyucu ailesiydi.
And he was a gentleman, unlike you.
Senin aksine çok centilmen bir beyefendiydi.
Well…
Şey…
But that man…
Ama o adam…
Besides,
Ayrıca
the boy chose to go with him.
onunla gitmeyi çocuk istedi.
Dieter!
Dieter!
Dieter?
Dieter.
They didn't come back?
Dönmediler mi?
This is Hartmann's study?
Burası Hartmann'ın çalışma odası mı?
Although at different times, they're all taken in the same place.
Farklı zamanlarda olsalar da tüm fotoğraflar aynı yerde çekilmiş.
Where is this…?
Burası neresi?
Johan.
Johan.
Who's this with him?
Yanındaki adam kim?
I see.
Anladım.
These were all taken in Kinderheim 511.
Tüm fotoğraflar 511. Yetimhane'de çekilmiş.
They start ten years ago and go until now.
10 sene önce başlayıp günümüze kadar devam ediyorlar.
All the members of the orphanage killed each other.
Yetimhanenin tüm üyeleri birbirini öldürdü.
Dieter…
Dieter.
Could he be…?
Yoksa o…
Dieter!
Dieter!
Wait there, Dieter! I'm coming!
Orada bekle Dieter! Geliyorum.
This boy cannot see it.
Bu çocuk göremiyor.
Hartmann!
Hartmann.
What Johan saw at that time,
Johan'ın o dönem görebildiğini
this boy cannot see it.
bu çocuk göremiyor.
No, it failed again.
Hayır, yine başarısız oldu.
This boy is not Johan, either.
Bu çocuk da Johan değil.
Everyone… Everyone died.
Herkes… Herkes öldü.
It was ten years ago.
Üzerinden 10 yıl geçti.
The instructors and orphans, all 50 of them died.
Eğitmenler ve yetimler. 50'si de öldü.
Johan watched it happen.
Johan ölmelerini seyretti.
From this place, he watched it all.
Buradan her şeyi seyretti.
Johan just watched them from this seat.
Johan bu koltuktan onları seyretti.
I asked him.
Ona sordum.
I asked him what exactly he did.
Tam olarak ne yaptığını sordum.
He told me.
Bana söyledi.
It's like adding this scrap of fabric soaked with oil into the fire.
Yağa batırılmış bir kumaş parçasını ateşe atmaya benziyor.
How about it?
Ne diyorsun?
Do you understand what he meant?
Ne demek istediğimi anlıyor musun?
"Hatred is born when people gather together."
"İnsanlar bir araya geldiğinde nefret doğar.
"I merely poured some oil onto this."
Ben sadece buna biraz yağ döktüm"
He said that! And he was only ten years old!
Böyle dedi ve daha 10 yaşındaydı.
And he did it.
Ve bunu başardı.
He made 50 people kill each other without lifting a finger of his own.
Kılını bile kıpırdatmadan 50 kişiye birbirini öldürttü.
It's your… your experiment
Onu böyle bir insana dönüştüren şey
Our experiment?
Deneyimiz mi?
No. That's not true.
Hayır, hiç de bile.
Not true at all.
Alakası yok.
What?
Ne?
It's true that Kinderheim 511 was
511. Yetimhane'nin bir deney tesisi olduğu doğru.
It was a project to create the perfect soldiers from the orphans.
Yetimlerden kusursuz askerler yaratmak için düzenlenmiş bir projeydi.
Now I think of it, that was a modest experiment.
Şimdi düşündüğümde bu, basit bir deneydi sadece.
So how about Johan? Was he a soldier?
Peki Johan'a ne oldu? Asker mi oldu?
That would be wrong.
Bu yanlış olurdu.
He was a natural-born leader.
Doğuştan bir liderdi.
He was destined to be on top.
Kaderinde zirveye çıkmak vardı.
There is no way we could have created a masterpiece like him.
Onun gibi bir şaheser yaratabilmemiz imkânsızdı.
He was more than human…
Johan bir insandan daha fazlasıydı…
Like a monster from the beginning.
En başından bir canavar gibiydi.
He made a prediction.
Bir tahminde bulundu.
"In the end, humans will hate and kill each other."
"Sonunda insanlar
What do you think Johan's goal was?
Sence Johan'ın amacı neydi?
This is what he told me.
Bana böyle dedi.
His goal was to be the last person alive at the end of the world.
Amacı dünya son bulduğunda hayatta kalan son insan olmaktı.
Dieter.
Dieter.
Tomorrow is dark.
Yarın karanlık.
You have to try and be like Johan, even just a little.
Biraz bile olsa Johan gibi olmaya çalışmalısın.
However…
Ancak…
Why isn't this working?
Bu neden işe yaramıyor?
Why can't you be like Johan?
Neden Johan gibi olamıyorsun?
Stop it, Hartmann! Hurt him any more and I'll shoot!
Kes şunu Hartmann! Ona daha fazla zarar verirsen ateş ederim!
Get out of here.
Defol buradan.
This doesn't concern you. Just get out of here.
Bu iş seni ilgilendirmez. Defol git buradan.
Dieter! Come down here.
Dieter! Aşağı in.
Dr. Tenma.
Dr. Tenma.
You want to know about Johan, right?
Johan'ı merak ediyorsun, değil mi?
What are you going to do when you know about him?
Onun hakkında bilgi alınca ne yapacaksın?
It'll be impossible for you to kill him when you find him.
Onu bulduğunda onu öldürmen imkânsız olacak.
Oh, well.
Peki.
I will tell you one thing.
Sana bir şey söyleyeyim.
In exchange, leave us be once I tell you.
Bunu söylemem karşılığında bizi yalnız bırak.
Find General Wolf.
General Wolf'u bul.
He was the one who discovered Johan's talent.
Johan'ın yeteneğini o keşfetti.
I'm sure he's alive somewhere.
Bir yerlerde sağ olduğuna eminim.
Was he the man in the photos I found in your study?
Çalışma odanda bulduğum fotoğraflardaki adam mı o?
The man pictured with Johan?
Johan'la fotoğrafı olan adam mı?
He was the one who brought Johan, so he knows everything.
Johan'ı getiren oydu, yani her şeyi biliyor.
Now, just go.
Şimdi defol.
Dieter!
Dieter!
You decide whether to come down or not!
Aşağı inip inmeyeceğine sen karar ver!
Don't worry.
Merak etme.
If Hartmann puts his finger on the rifle's trigger, I will shoot him.
Hartmann parmağını tetiğe koyarsa onu vururum.
Dieter.
Dieter.
Make the decision yourself!
Kararını kendin ver!
It's impossible for you to leave me, right? Dieter.
Yanımdan gitmen imkânsız, değil mi Dieter?
You're my child, after all.
Sonuçta sen benim oğlumsun.
As you can see, Dr. Tenma.
Gördüğün gibi Dr. Tenma.
Now, get out of here.
Şimdi defol git buradan.
Dieter.
Dieter.
That's good. Don't worry.
Güzel. Endişelenme.
Slowly, just like that.
Yavaş yavaş. Aynen öyle.
Dieter, come back.
Dieter, geri gel.
My sweet Dieter!
Canım Dieter'ım!
Do you think you will survive away from me, Dieter?
Benden uzakta hayatta kalabileceğini mi düşünüyorsun Dieter?
Don't move, or I'll shoot.
Kıpırdama yoksa ateş ederim!
I love you, Dieter!
Seni seviyorum Dieter!
The world is a horrible place, and tomorrow is dark!
Dünya korkunç bir yer, yarın karanlık.
Mr. Tenma told me.
Bay Tenma söyledi.
That tomorrow will be a good day.
Yarın güzel bir gün olacakmış.
Dieter!
Dieter!
Be brave. There's nothing to be afraid of.
Cesur ol. Korkacak hiçbir şey yok.
Dieter…
Dieter.
Dieter!
Dieter!
Listen, you will get on the bus from here.
Bak, buradan otobüse bineceksin.
Get off at the Kühnen Street.
Kühnen Sokağı'nda in.
There is an orphanage in front of the stop.
Durağın önünde bir yetimhane var.
Give this to Ms. Erna Tietze in the orphanage.
Bunu yetimhanedeki Bayan Erna Tietze'ye ver.
She may seem a little scary, but she's actually very kind at heart.
Biraz deli birine benzeyebilir ama çok iyi kalpli bir kadındır.
Good luck.
Bol şans.
There is a reason I can't go into town, so this is goodbye.
Şehre gelemememin bir sebebi var, yani burada vedalaşacağız.
The bus should be here in two or three minutes. Goodbye.
Otobüs iki, üç dakikaya gelir. Hoşça kal.
Practice soccer, okay?
Futbol çalış, tamam mı?
No, you can't come with me.
Hayır, benimle gelemezsin.
Hey.
Hey.
Dieter.
Dieter.
I told you not to come with me.
Benimle gelme, dedim.
Don't come with me.
Benimle gelme.